all right so I have to make this video
somebody somebody I'm I'm doing
container D commands and like what's CTR
and LBG answered the the question about
you know what's the difference between
container D and doer and I love this
answer I just have to share it LBG DN
says to put it short darker is container
D plus other stuff on top of it that's
useless for
kubernetes and that's that's kind of my
take on it
um this is a very short video so of the
container engines that exist and and and
maybe maybe I'll go to make a point mode
here we go this is make a point mode
behold um also gives me a better
thumbnail
so there let's go through the container
engines right so I believe it's called
The Container runtime interface it's a
kubernetes thing it's kubernetes has got
all these acronyms that
Define pieces of architecture that have
to be there again kubernetes is
specification it's not software it
specifies how software should be and how
it should work uh Creo still better and
we're going to that's a great fight to
have okay uh and and so here we
have uh you know I'm using container de
most people these days I'm just going to
cut to the chase everybody uses
container de today a few uh people you
know use Creo which is an even light
we're going to get into what the
differences are but a few people use
Creo Almost Never nobody still uses
Docker Community Edition or Docker as
their container engine particularly
since I think it's been now 2 years
since Cooper dtis officially kicked
Docker
out and said we don't want any
Docker and apparent apparently my
reactions from my Mac Pro are in favor
of kicking Docker out and so there's no
Docker right why no Docker Docker is the
devil I've made videos about this before
the docker company original founder of
Darker has long gone moved on to pursue
other interests and darker is seriously
the devil um uh it doesn't have a CRT
term no it doesn't and that's the
biggest argument against it which we
will talk about in a second so um the
now that Docker is out and and let let's
just really quickly summarize why Docker
is a devil and why it's out number one
Docker has pulled fast ones on people in
the business world for a long time and
the people in the open source world the
company actually pulled a rug out from
several open source projects that said
you can't store your stuff here and they
end up making charging money even though
they're open source and it was a huge
Fiasco they couldn't even get to their
own containers and the entire open
source World said whoa we're out of here
and so what do they do they all go to
the GitHub container registry these days
GCR is where you'll see images coming
getting pulled from or they decided to
run their own Registries like Harbor
like uh kubernetes itself and a bunch of
other places because they're just done
with Docker uh there are still some
images that are being hosted on Docker
Hub but nobody you know who's paying any
attention wants any dependency on this
this horrible horrible company Docker
also turned around and tried to charge
uh everybody who was running Docker on
the desktop uh money overnight they gave
him like six months and then they they
pushed it out further because all of a
sudden they were saying hey Enterprises
we're going bankrupt and now you have to
pay and so everybody clamored this was
two years ago everybody clamored to try
to find an alternative for the desktop
to run containers for small projects and
things like that and people tried pod
man desktop there was a at one point
there was a uh what was the other one um
uh open open what was the open container
Quay yeah there have been tons of alter
it turned out pod man usually the winter
when it comes to like desktop container
engines and tools uh podman is kind of
one in that space it's you Red Hat
whether you love them or hate them
they've decided it's also safer because
it doesn't you know have that socket
issue going if you don't want any of
that is then you just have to study
containers and in short darker is the
devil nobody wants to use it anymore and
nobody should use it and so what are you
going to use right the entire kubernetes
infrastructure was based on Docker
originally well that's no longer been
the case hasn't been the case for
something like two years so what is the
case now is that a lot of things have
emerged to replace it and I'm going to
name the top three things uh we're
talking okay we're talking about
container engines right now not uh tools
for running containers on your desktop
they're different so podman and Docker
uh scopio builda all those things that
you use to deal with containers and move
them around those tools and stuff those
are not in this the scope of
conversation right now set those aside
what we're talking about is a container
engine in other words I want to put a
container engine on a thing because I
want to run kubernetes or I want to run
mini Cube or I want to run which is
kubernetes or I want to run n Nomad
right uh and all of these things require
containers and and some of them share
they all have they all have similarities
in particular Nomad and kubernetes are
uh very interesting because they both
require container engine and they both
require something that started as a
kubernetes standard called the container
network interface um so the cni and
that's the way the container does
networking and how it talks to each
other and how containers network with
each other and so these are all related
to the conversation um they all are
built obviously container these
containers we're talking about are not
jails they're not BSD they're all built
on something called lxc and a lot of
people would argue from the L community
that lxc is the one true way to use a
container and it's really low level and
that uses something called c groups and
there's actually a lowl component called
run C which has become the abstraction
of how to run a container uh on top of
lxc and that has now become sort of a
dependent piece of this all of these
things use run C why is this important
because all of the container enges that
I'm going to talk about have different
layers of complexity and bloat that are
layered on top of run C more or less
okay so Creo which our friend has been
mentioning is by far the lightest it is
super duper lightweight it's this teeny
tiny wrapper of runc it's pretty much
just runc and for that reason if you
need to debug a container or you want to
do Docker type things like you know exec
into a container or see it or LS it or
remove the image and all these different
things a lot of those functions are not
included with the command line tools to
use uh to use uh uh that uh there are a
number of utilities that relate to all
of this uh new container engines stuff
some of which I actually kind of
deficient skills wise in uh one of them
is cctl so uh CR CTL this is called
container runtime uh interface so all
the container engines since kubernetes
made the the the the Declaration Thou
shalt Define and follow the container
runtime interface every container engine
on the planet that matters uses CRI and
so this tool has been maintained that
interfaces directly with anything that
speaks CRI now but the container runtime
interface doesn't cover everything you
would want to do with do or pod man and
so you may be like thinking oh my God
where did my commands go right and that
is because the container runtime
interface has been designed for
kubernetes that's where the comment at
the beginning of the video comes in uh
that it it's it's not the stuff that you
would want to do on a desktop so it's
eliminated a lot of those things that
you might want uh For Better or Worse
right and then so each container runtime
engine has decided okay how much are we
going to add on top of the base
functionality of run C and C and cni the
container networking interface switch
defines how they talk to each other so
um you know if you're trying to if
you're just trying to get containers to
work uh on your desktop this is not the
video for you this is the video for
which engine should I pick so Creo is
c-o is when we first used it two years
ago was rather immature and it didn't
really work and it had some bugs in it
um and but it but since it's it's come
around I'm not going to use it though
for reasons we'll talk about later it's
the lightest weight it's the smallest
engine you can possibly run on a node uh
whether it's a virtual or real node
being a machine um and you you know it's
the smallest thing you can get it's just
B Baseline layer on top of run SE uh and
it step up from that and you get
container D container D is kind of the
Legacy from Docker and Docker CE uh and
as actually unfortunately the packages
if you want a package install of
container d uh you still have to go to
the doer project uh uh for those things
and that is why I wrote my own uh
installer for container D based on
container D's
documentation uh that is not a package
but this is all the stuff that you would
get from a package this is how you
install container D this adds bash
completion for container D this installs
run C it re installs the the container D
plugins for cni and all that stuff now
why would you pick container D over over
run over uh just um you know Creo uh
Creo is the defa for open shift yeah but
open shift is a red hat offering and
they have more control over the
container engines they don't want people
open shift is more of a one solution
meets you know come is is good for
everybody kind of thing and they want
lightweight you know so they don't want
to impact their thing Plus usually if
you're doing open shift you're already
deploying red hat and so red you know
open shift plus red hat equals you know
joy for them in Enterprise um and and so
they they they kind of control the whole
ecosystem so they really don't want
people poking around in the container
engine but if you're me or you're any
other of other people in their home lab
or some other thing sometimes you want
to use that container engine on that
node for other purposes or you want to
you just don't trust uh the minimalism
of Creo and other things like that
because you really want to see what's
going on when kubernetes stops working
and you want to go you know look K you
know get under the hood or whatever and
see what's actually going on and the
only way you can actually see what's
going on in a container engine is um uh
should be yeah well it's it is now Creo
was not battle tested two years ago it
was not it was throwing all kind of
errors in our test cases at work and so
we decided not to do it um you know
these Technologies are evolving all the
time so you probably want to reevaluate
every year whether you want to do it but
if you're deploying a cluster and that
cluster is going to be around for a year
or two uh which is probably a bad idea
by the way you should be automatically
updating your clusters pretty frequently
otherwise you're going to get you know
day two problems in your
Enterprise so what container engine you
use that decision is largely up to you
uh but if you want more access you've
been be using it for five that doesn't
surprise me a lot of a lot of advanced
people have been using uh Creo for a
long time and making it work um I'm just
telling you that when we tried it in our
Enterprise that the people who did it it
wasn't me they had an exceptional number
of complications with the container
engine in our Enterprise now we might
have had Hardware concerns that were
different um but you know obviously you
have to test all these things out Creo
is the lightest weight therefore
technically it probably is going to be
the least likely to have problems once
it gets stable because there's not a lot
of things to maintain but it also Expos
es the least amount of things to you
under the hood you have to go through uh
kubernetes or Nomad or whatever it is to
get to the stuff that you want to see um
about the container engine there's no
way to you know open the hood or go
under the car and see how it's working
you can't you know SSH into the box and
then run a command that doesn't have
anything to do with the with the thing
using the container engine and that can
be that can be problematic and by the
way that is primarily the difference
between these things so Creo gives you
almost zero access to of the things that
are happening under the hood um you
found some small issues and open PRS for
them okay nice um but and then and then
but but you know it's it's lightweight
blah blah blah container D is kind of
the step up from that it's not Docker
but it's heavily inspired by Docker and
currently controlled by Docker and I
think that's super important container
container D has not yet broken free of
the docker umbrella if you want to
install container is a separate project
but the project and the package installs
and everything are still coming from the
docker the docker team uh if I'm wrong
about that please you know put it in the
comments be nice you know I'm just going
on what I last heard so but as far as I
know as of this moment the container d
project still has ties with Docker it's
so much so that you can't apt install
container D unless you add the docker
bloat which includes adding the literal
Docker Hub uh package repository to your
app repos just to install it by using
apt install if you're on a buntu and I'm
not doing that so I wrote a script to do
it in the official container D
alternative way which is you know
download the service and add it to
system D download you know the container
D stuff download runy download the
plugins you know add an Etsy an Etsy
Etsy uh Control G uh config Tomo file
and modify it using a Tomo python script
which is all in my script you can go
look at it and and that's all the stuff
that a package install would do for you
but you know it's not a package it's
ugly um should somebody make a package
for under the app repo that is coming
from a distant repository for container
D I think they should but I don't want
to be the one to do it and if it if it
does happen it should come from the
container re project which right now
doesn't seem motivated to do that they
just want to continue to use the one
that's being maintained by Docker so I I
don't know the reason for that but it's
important that you know that you're not
getting you're not free of Docker uh you
know things in fact there are still some
pieces even of kubernetes that used to
be Docker you have to install the docker
CE package to get them that might
changed the last two years I'm about to
find out so that's a lot to talk about
what about Docker CE Community Edition
yeah you can just install Docker C
Community Edition Docker we're talking
about the desktop thing the docker same
Docker command everything you can use
that you can use that that will put in
the all the container engine you want on
your on your nodes if you want but it's
got a lot of extra stuff there that
doesn't need to be there uh you can use
Docker if you want if you want to
install darker on all those nodes you
can do that too you can install podb on
those nodes and any of those tools will
but at each stage in the game you you
you you've added more bloat um to give
you one solid example which I think is a
bad example but I'm going to cite it for
you anyway I think this is an anti-
pattern let me just say it right up
front but our business when we my the
place that I work when I first got here
they had people using this I it makes me
sick to even say this because it's such
a bad practice um H yeah extra tax
service all kind of thing we had people
that were using they didn't have Docker
on their desktop and they weren't
allowed to install it so we had system
administrators who needed to use Docker
to for all the normal Docker things
right for getting an image and compiling
an image and creating a Docker file and
all those things right they were
actually reusing kubernetes node
machines as their personal Docker space
and so they would ssh in they would ssh
in his root because they had root access
the rest of user base didn't and they
said well I need Docker I don't want to
put on my desktop or whatever and so
they would SSH route and they would use
Docker using the the doer command and
they and their their container images
and all their stuff would end up getting
intermixed with the stuff being managed
by kubernetes on that note that is a
major major violation of best PR best
practice one of the biggest
anti-patterns in history I I can't
believe they did it and and they they
did this because they said they didn't
have any other way to use
darker I think that's totally stupid
thank you for the follow I thought that
was totally stupid I was like why are
you doing this this is so dangerous and
then and then and then the other guys
were saying well we can't administer our
endpoint nodes unless we can use Docker
and I'm like what are you talking about
they said well we need to get in there
and see what's going on in the container
engine and to be fair the container
engine doer container engine in
kubernetes was broken back then and
there were certain cases where the
images would stick around and they would
bloat out the container engine does
anybody remember this this is kubernetes
version whatever I don't remember what
version it was but there was a time when
kubernetes had a legitimate bug in it
that caused containers to sit there
forever and not ever get cleaned out and
the only way to clean up those images
was to go SSH over with Docker and then
delete all the extraneous images and
make sure they weren't being used by
kubernetes which if you're a kubernetes
admin I mean the whole you know promise
of kubernetes is to save you from that
crap and they did not do that oh my God
and it was it was horrible I don't ever
want to go back to that World um you
know it's been two or three years since
I really looked at that level of
kubernetes that deeply I'm doing it now
in my home lab but the point I'm trying
to make is um if if you didn't get if
you weren't burned by people who have
been burned by not being able to
manipulate the images that are in the
container runtime engine on their on
their endpoint nodes people who have
been burned by light like we were
they're very very leery of Creo because
they don't have the access to do that
they don't they don't have the same
debugging and administration access to
the underlying container image that was
absolutely essential to restoring
kubernetes functionality when that bug
existed and so they've been burned by
that and they're like oh hell no I am
not doing that I want access to my
container engine you know attack surface
and security or not I don't care I'm
going to go do it and maybe they have
other you know bad reasons like I need a
Docker engine someplace and I don't want
to put on my desktop because Docker I
have to pay for it now which is stupid
that's totally stupid don't do that but
if but that so they've been burned by it
so so a lot of people have sort of
landed on this middle ground and and the
middle ground I I personally believe the
most po computer container engine right
now um and is yeah I'll definitely link
to the ZET um I I think that the most
the most uh the most popular container
engine today particularly for home Labs
is container d uh for that reason it has
the level of access for tweaking and
watching what's going on with your
images even if it's just for learning
purposes um and you know it doesn't it
doesn't hobble you when you try to see
what's actually happening under the hood
um like Creo does but it also you know
it it it's it's kind of on that side so
it gives you more access into it so
people like me that are uncomfortable
with the absolute minimum of by the way
I did try to run a kubernetes cluster
with Creo and tested it when I did my
last kubernetes cluster and then I
realized that I couldn't do anything in
the IM and that was when I decided I did
not want anything to do with it um
because I I wanted to be able to to
Tinker and that is why that I have
chosen container D all of my peers at
work including the ones that by the way
the people who did that in the
cluster sorry for the swear word they're
gone now all of them they've all went on
to do other things the team that I'm
with now they know their they know
what they're doing I'm super happy to
have them as teammates why is my
reaction not
working that makes me sad There we go so
that is why I am using container d uh
container D or Creo that's what I would
use um there may be other cont container
runtime enges I don't know about them
let me know in the comments uh I should
know about them those are the other ones
that really matter though in my opinion